

# Guillaume Garrigos

## Curriculum Vitae

Personal information and contact	_		_			
Parcanal Intormation and contact			l • C	and the second second		the second resident
	-	'Arcona	IINTOR	mation	วทด	CONTACT

- Born in Toulouse (France), May 8th 1989.
- Université Paris Cité, Place Aurélie Nemours, 75013 Paris, France.
- @ guillaume.garrigos@lpsm.paris
- http://guillaume-garrigos.com

## Current position (2018–)

position Maître de conférences at Université Paris Cité

affiliation Laboratoire de Probabilités, Statistique et Modélisation

research optimization, statistical machine learning, inverse problems, image and signal pro-

interests cessing, algorithms and continuous dynamical systems, tame optimization.

## Previous positions (2012–2018)

2017–2018 **Post-doc**, École Normale Supérieure, Paris, France.

Main collaborator : Gabriel Peyré (ENS, CNRS, INRIA)

Research themes: inverse problems, signal and image processing, optimization

2015–2017 **Post-doc**, *Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia*, Genoa, Italy.

Main collaborators : Lorenzo Rosasco (IIT, MIT) and Silvia Villa (IIT)

Research themes: optimization and regularization methods for machine learning.

2012–2015 **Ph.D.**, Université de Montpellier & Universidad Santa Maria, France & Chile.

Supervisors: Hédy Attouch (UM) and Juan Peypouquet (USM)

Subject: Dynamical systems for tame optimization and multi-objective problems

## **Education and Degrees**

- 2013 Agrégation de Mathématiques, ranked 147/323.
- 2010–2012 Master, Université de Montpellier, Mathématiques, Statistiques et Applications.
- 2007–2010 Licence, Université de Montpellier, Mathématiques Fondamentales et Appliquées.
  - 2007 Baccalauréat, Lycée Diderot, Narbonne.

### **Publications**

#### Publications in international specialized journals.

- o G. Garrigos, L. Rosasco and S. Villa. *Accelerated iterative regularization via dual diagonal descent*, SIAM Journal on Optimization, Vol. 31, No. 1, pp. 754–784, 2021.
- G. Garrigos, L. Rosasco and S. Villa. Thresholding gradient methods in Hilbert spaces: support identification and linear convergence, ESAIM: Control, Optimisation and Calculus of Variations, Vol. 26 (28), 2020.
- o G. Garrigos, L. Rosasco and S. Villa. *Iterative regularization via dual diagonal descent*, Journal of Mathematical Imaging and Vision, Vol. 60, No. 2, pp. 189–215, 2018.
- o G. Garrigos, L. Rosasco and S. Villa. *Convergence of the Forward-Backward algorithm:* beyond the worst case with geometry, Mathematical Programming, Vol. 198, pp. 937–996, 2023
- H. Attouch, G. Garrigos and X. Goudou. A dynamic gradient approach to Pareto optimization with nonsmooth convex objective functions, Journal of Mathematical Analysis and Applications, Vol. 422, No. 1, pp. 741–771, 2015.
- P. Frankel, G. Garrigos and J. Peypouquet. Splitting methods with variable metric for KL functions and general convergence rates, Journal of Optimization Theory and Applications, Vol. 165, No. 3, pp. 874–900, 2015.

#### Publications in international conferences.

- J. Chen, R. Yuan, G. Garrigos and R. M. Gower. SAN: Stochastic Average Newton Algorithm for Minimizing Finite Sums, 25th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), PMLR, Vol. 151, pp. 279–318, 2022.
- o G. Garrigos, L. Rosasco and S. Villa. Sparse Multiple Kernel Learning: Support Identification via Mirror Stratifiability, IEEE 26th European Signal Processing Conference (EUSIPCO), pp. 1077–1081, 2018.
- J. Fadili, G. Garrigos, J. Malick and G. Peyré. Model Consistency for Learning with Mirror-Stratifiable Regularizers, 22nd International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), PMLR, Vol. 89, pp. 1236–1244, 2019.
- o G. Garrigos, L. Rosasco and S. Villa. *Iterative regularization via a dual diagonal descent method*, 9th NIPS Workshop on Optimization for Machine Learning, 2016.

#### Preprints.

- o G. Garrigos, R. M. Gower and F. Schaipp. Function Value Learning: Adaptive Learning Rates Based on the Polyak Stepsize and Function Splitting in ERM. Preprint on arXiv:2307.14528.
- M. Hihat, S. Gaïffas, G. Garrigos and S. Bussy. Online Inventory Problems: Beyond the i.i.d. Setting with Online Convex Optimization. Preprint on arXiv:2307.06048.
- o J. Domke, G. Garrigos and R. M. Gower. *Provable convergence guarantees for black-box variational inference*. Preprint on arXiv:2306.03638. ■
- o G. Garrigos and R. M. Gower. *Handbook of Convergence Theorems for (Stochastic) Gradient Methods.* Preprint on arXiv:2301.11235. □
- G. Garrigos. Square distance functions are Polyak-Łojasiewicz and vice-versa. Preprint on arXiv:2301.10332.
- o H. Attouch and G. Garrigos. *Multiobjective optimization : an inertial dynamical approach to Pareto optima*. Preprint on arXiv:1506.02823. ☐

## Miscellaneous

- 2019 PEPS grant funded by INSMI (CNRS), 3,5k EUR.
- 2017 SMAI-MODE Dodu Prize for the best young researcher talk: *Structured sparsity in inverse problems and support recovery with mirror-stratifiable functions.*

## Responsibilities

#### Student supervision

- 2023 Julien Marie-Anne. Undergrad project.
- 2023 Lucas Ketels. Undergrad thesis.
- 2021-2024 Massil Hihat. PhD thesis.

#### Seminars, Events

- 2019 Co-organizer of the workshop "Regularisation for Inverse Problems and Machine Learning", in Paris •
- 2018 Co-organizer of the session "Dimensionality reduction tools for learning: A sketchy session" for the International Symposium on Mathematical Programming (ISMP)
- 2017 Organizer of the NORIA group meeting at ENS
- 2017 Co-organizer of the Machine Learning summer school RegML 2017, in Oslo 3
- 2015–2017 Organizer of the Machine Learning Tutorials, between the LCSL groups at IIT (Genova) and MIT (Boston)